Finding aid to the Elisabeth Luce Moore papers SSC.MS.00225
Sophia Smith Collection
Elisabeth Luce Moore papers
1928-1989
Sophia Smith Collection
Moore, Elisabeth Luce
SSC.MS.00225
15 boxes (13 linear feet)
Journalist; Editor; Trustee, State University of New York; YWCA official; and International relations specialist. Papers include an scrapbooks; oral history; correspondence; photographs and clippings; travel files from trips to Asia, Europe, Australia, and China; speeches and writings; and files pertaining to organizations concerned with international relations, education, and international development, among them the Young Women's Christion Association and SUNY.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections. Collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be somewhat difficult to use. Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice. Use copies of audio cassettes of oral history need to be made upon request.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Elisabeth Luce Moore in 1988, 19991, and 2011. Accession numbers: 88S-24, 91S-25, 11S-33.
Biographical / Historical
Elisabeth Luce was born in China to Presbyterian Board missionaries, April 4, 1903. She graduated from Wellesley College in 1924, where she later served on the Board of Trustees. She married Maurice T. Moore in 1926; they had two sons, Thompson and Michael.
She is the sister of Henry R. Luce, founder of Time Magazine, and early in her career she worked as editor and writer for his periodicals. She was also active in volunteer social work, working with such agencies as the New York Junior League and the National and International YWCA, serving as chair of the YWCA's foreign division in 1944. She was chair of the Nation Council of the USO during World War II, and she served on the advisory committee of the Economic Cooperation Administration, which administered the Marshall Plan. She was a delegate to the International Conference of Women in 1951. Luce Moore served as board chair of the Institute of International Education, which administers such exchange programs as the Fulbright Scholar Program. She has also served as vice-president of United Services to China, and as trustee of the China Institute of America, the Asia Foundation, and the United Board for Christian Higher Education. In 1968 she was appointed by Governor Nelson Rockefeller as chair of the Board of Trustees of the State University of New York, the first woman to hold that job.
She holds honorary degrees from Columbia University, Duke University, Princeton University, Trinity University, the State University of New York, Claremont Graduate Center, Wellesley College, Hamilton College, Adelphi College, Western College, and Silliman University in the Philippines. She has also received numerous awards for her work, among them the Elisabeth Blackwell Medal from Hobart and William Smith Colleges, the National Institute of Social Sciences Medal, the Readers' Digest Award, and the Order of the Brilliant Star from the People's Republic of China. Elisabeth Luce Moore died on February 9, 2002.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Scope and Contents
The Elisabeth Luce Moore Papers include an oral history (1989); scrapbooks (1944-68, 1965); correspondence (1928-85); photographs and clippings (1938-59, 1964-86); awards; travel files from trips to Asia, Europe, Australia, and China(including correspondence, photographs, clippings and notes, all dating from 1950-72); speeches and writings (1920s, 1949-83); organization files, among them the Young Women's Christion Association (YWCA) and SUNY (1944-84); and subject files (1944, 1961-75). Strengths of the collection include Luce/Moore family correspondence, and material pertaining to organizations concerned with international relations, education, and development.
Asia--Description and travel--Sources; China--Description and travel--Sources; Family--United States--History--20th century; International relations--History--20th century--Sources; International education--History--Sources; Women journalists--United States--Biography; Women--Congresses--History; correspondence; photographs; clippings; Oral histories; Organization files; Awards; diaries; Speeches; Moore, Elisabeth Luce; Luce family; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.--History; State University of New York--History--Sources; Lautz, Terrill E.; Moore, Elisabeth Luce; Lautz, Terrill E.
- Elisabeth Luce Moore oral history recordings by Terry Lautz, 1985 June 18 - 1987 February 21; 2011-S-0033; Lautz, Terrill E.; 0.5 linear feet (1 box) (Box 1)
  Lautz, Terrill E.
  - Oral history recording labelled "ELM/Luce Foundation", 1986 September 18; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restrictions designated by the SSC: RESTRICTED--Closed until use copies can be made.
  - Oral history recording labelled "ELM/NYC, Texas", 1986 July 29; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)
  - Oral history recording labelled "Elisabeth Moore, Weston, CT", 1985 June 28; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)
  - Oral history recording labelled "Eliz. Luce Moore, Weston, CT, #2", 1985 June 28; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)
  - Oral history recording labelled "ELM, NYC, Texas, USO, CK5", 1987 January 29; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)
  - Oral history recording labelled " ELM, Wellesley", 1986 May 01; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)
  - Oral history recording labelled "ELM interview, YWCA", 1986 April 08; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)
  - Oral history recording labelled "ELM interview, SUNY", 1986 March 27; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)
  - Oral history recording labelled "ELM, family & SUNY", 1986 February 05; 1986 March 27; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)
  - Oral history recording labelled "United Board, Asia Foundation", 1987 February 27; 2011-S-0033 (Box 1)